<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Brigitte Hofmeister on Brigitte Hofmeister</title>
    <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Brigitte Hofmeister on Brigitte Hofmeister</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018 Brigitte Hofmeister</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Web Application for Undergraduate Genetics Education</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/undergrad-genetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/undergrad-genetics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This project is in progress.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing an interest for web development, this project aims to join my interests: software development and genetics.
This web application aims to teach undergraduate students principles of genetics with problem solving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, &lt;em&gt;Inherit Logic&lt;/em&gt; contains two modules: Cricket and Mendelpede. Cricket focuses on teaching students about
codons and frameshift mutations. Mendelpede focuses on transmission genetics.
In both modules, students perform virtual experiments to learn the underlying genetics principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Cricket, there are 10 different scenarios for students to go through. Students are given a starting
set of phage strains and must plate them on &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; to accomplish the scenario&amp;rsquo;s goal. While plating,
random frameshift mutations may arise and different strains can be combined to create recombinant individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mendelpede, students are given a starting set of &amp;ldquo;pedes&amp;rdquo; with 5 variable phenotypic
characteristics. By performing crosses between different pedes, students need to
identify the mode of inheritance for each trait and dominance. There are also quizzes
for students to determine the genotype of a set of pedes so instructors can see how students are doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cricket has been used successfully in two semesters of an advanced undergraduate genetics course at UGA.
Mendelpede has beeen used for one semester in both a graduate and undergraduate course. Based on student feedback,
students enjoyed using the software as an educational tool and liked the interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Built using the MEAN stack (MongoDB, Express, Node.js, and Angular), this application is visually appealling. Where ever possible, standard practices in software engineering where used. Back end, front end, and underlying genetics are unit tested to ensure functional code as development continues.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced JBrowse plugins for epigenomics data visualization</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/jbrowse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/jbrowse/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stable inheritance of DNA methylation allows creation of epigenotype maps and the study of epiallele inheritance patterns in the absence of genetic variation</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/methyl-inherit/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/methyl-inherit/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Arabidopsis protein kinase D6PKL3 is involved in formation of distinct plasma-membrane aperture domains on the pollen surface</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/arabidopsis_d6pkl3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/arabidopsis_d6pkl3/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining ATAC-seq with nuclei sorting for discovery of cis-regulatory regions in plant genomes</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/atac-seq/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/atac-seq/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenomics Visualization</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenomics-visualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenomics-visualization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Epigenomics is the study of genome-wide distributions of chromatin modifications.
Our knowledge of epigenomics has drastically improved with next-generation sequencing (NGS) with techniques like whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) and chromatin immunoprecipation sequencing (ChIP-seq).
With the large quantities of data being produced, data visualization is an important step for quality control and exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous software programs exist to visualize genomics data; most popular is the genome browser.
These existing programs focus on a limited subset of data types such as mRNA-seq and single-nucleotide polymorphisms. Beyond ChIP-seq, there is very little support for visualizing epigenomics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have developed additional tools, plugins, for the genome browser JBrowse that support epigenomics data.
Specifically, I have created ways to view context-dependent DNA methylation from WGBS. The methylation context is very important to its function, particularly the combination of contexts in a region. Traditional genome browsers require the DNA methylation contexts as separate &amp;ldquo;tracks&amp;rdquo; which makes it extremely difficult to see combinations and patterns.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-methylation.git&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;methylation plugin&lt;/a&gt; I have developed allows for all methylation contexts to be displayed on one track with the context differentiate by color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small RNA are also important in epigenetics as they can regulate gene expression and impact DNA methylation.
Traditional browsers support small RNA-sequencing data but are missing features specifically useful for small RNA-seq. Specifically, the size of a small RNA is indicative of function.
I have developed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-smallrna.git&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;small RNA-plugin&lt;/a&gt; for JBrowse which colors reads based on size and improves visualization by separating reads from the plus and minus strand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, ChIP-seq and similar techniques such as ATAC-seq, DNaseI-seq, Mnase-seq, are supported in JBrowse. However, it is missing features that are useful specifically in epigenomics.
For example, in ATAC-seq, it is beneficial to know strand-specific coverage (not currently support by JBrowse).
I have created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-strandedplot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt; that easily supports these strand-specific coverage tracks. This plugin is also very useful for coverage views of mRNA-seq and smRNA-seq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the epigenomics plugins, I have also created a plugin which makes taking
browser screenshots easier and with customized view options. This plugin leverages &lt;a href=&#34;https://phantomjscloud.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;PhantomJS Cloud&lt;/a&gt; to do the screenshot and is able to output images in PNG, JPG, and PDF. &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-screenshot&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The screenshot plugin&lt;/a&gt; is particularly useful for scientific data communication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generational Epigenetic Inheritance</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenetic-inheritance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenetic-inheritance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the combination of bisulfite conversion and high-throughput sequencing techniques, it is now possible to generate genome-wide single base resolution maps of cytosine methylation, referred to as whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS).
This has revolutionized the way scientists study epigenetics.
&lt;strong&gt;Epigenetics&lt;/strong&gt; is the study of heritable changes in gene expression that occur independently from changes in nucleotide sequence.
Before WGBS, methylation could only be determined in small regions at a time or at low resolution, but now it is possible to track single methylation polymorphisms across generations.
This technique to experimental and natural populations to understand epigenetic variation and effects of mutations on methylation polymorphisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am specifically interested in the generation, heritability, and stability of spontaneous epialleles both meiotically and mitotically.
&lt;strong&gt;Epiallele&lt;/strong&gt; describes a heritable allele that varies in chromatin state.
The most interesting, and most rare, of these epialleles are spontaneous epialleles, where the change in chromatin state occurs independent of changes in DNA sequence.
Several spontaneous epialleles are known in plants, such as &lt;em&gt;Lcyc&lt;/em&gt; gene, which causes altered flower morphology, and &lt;em&gt;colorless non-ripening&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;CNR&lt;/em&gt;) epiallele, which prevents pigmentation in tomatoes.
These epialleles have been well studied and documented in the literature, although they offer limited insight into directed applications of directed epimutagenisis and the heritability of epialleles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project aims to determine if epialleles are stable across generations and follow Mendelian inheritance, which are requirements for successful introduction into breeding programs.&lt;br /&gt;
Previous work from the Schmitz lab with &lt;em&gt;Arabidopsis thaliana&lt;/em&gt; mutation accumulation lines revealed the existence of spontaneous epialleles between early and late generation lines.
Using WGBS from successive generations of two MA lines, I determined that approximately 99.998% of methylated regions in the genome are faithfully inherited to the next generation.
For breeding programs, spontaneous epialleles must also be inherited following Mendelian laws.
With a genetic cross between two MA lines, WGBS was obtained for the parents of the cross and 20 F2 individuals.
The parents only had about 40 distinguishing mutations, which required the creation of a novel algorithm to generate a genetic map using only DNA methylation, termed an &lt;strong&gt;epigenotype map&lt;/strong&gt;.
The epigenotype map allowed me to explore the inheritance patterns of differing epialleles between the parents and approximately half of these epialleles showed expected inheritance.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the origin and evolutionary consequences of gene body DNA methylation</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/origin-gbm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/origin-gbm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Base J represses genes at the end of polycistronic gene clusters in Leishmania major by promoting RNAP II termination</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/l-major_base_j/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/l-major_base_j/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FASTmC: A Suite of Predictive Models for Nonreference-Based Estimations of DNA Methylation</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/fastmc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/fastmc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Histone H3 Variant Regulates RNA Polymerase II Transcription Termination and Dual Strand Transcription of siRNA Loci in Trypanosoma brucei</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/t-brucei_base_j/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/publication/t-brucei_base_j/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
