<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Brigitte Hofmeister</title>
    <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Brigitte Hofmeister</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Brigitte Hofmeister</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://bhofmei.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenetic Inheritance</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenetic-inheritance/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenetic-inheritance/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epigenomics Vizualization</title>
      <link>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenomics-visualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bhofmei.github.io/project/epigenomics-visualization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Epigenomics is the study of genome-wide distribtuions of chromatin modifications.
Our knowledge of epigenomics has drastically improved with next-generation sequencing (NGS) with techniques like whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) and chromatin immunoprecifpation sequencing (ChIP-seq).
With the large quantities of data being produced, data vizualization is an important step for quality control and exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous software programs exist to visualize genomics data; most popular is the genome browser.
These existing programs focus on a limited subset of data types such as mRNA-seq and single-nucleotide polymorphisms. Beyond ChIP-seq, there is almost no support for intuitively visualizing epigenomics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been working on developing additonal tools, plugins, for the genome browser JBrowse that support epigenomics data.
Specifically, I have created ways to view context-dependent DNA methylation from WGBS. The methylation context is very important to its function, particularly the combination of contexts in a region. Traditional genome browsers require the DNA methylation contexts as separate &amp;ldquo;tracks&amp;rdquo; which makes it extremely difficult to see combinations and patterns.
The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-methylation.git&#34;&gt;methylation plugin&lt;/a&gt; I have developed allows for all methylation contexts to be displayed on one track with the context differentiate by color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Small RNA are also important in epigenetics as they can regulate gene expression and impact DNA methylation.
Traiditional browsers support small RNA-sequencing data but are missing features specifically useful for small RNA-seq. Specifically, the size of a small RNA is indiciative of function.
I have developed a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-smallrna.git&#34;&gt;small RNA-plugin&lt;/a&gt; for JBrowse which colors reads based on size and improves visualization by separating reads from the plus and minus strand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, ChIP-seq and similar techniques such as ATAC-seq, DNaseI-seq, Mnase-seq, are supported in JBrowse. However, it is missing features that are useful specifically in epigenomics.
For example, in ATAC-seq, it is beneficial to know strand-specific coverage (not currently support by JBrowse).
I have created a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bhofmei/jbplugin-strandedplot&#34;&gt;plugin&lt;/a&gt; that easily supports these strand-specific coverage tracks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>